<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="ceki at qos ddoott ch ">Ceki Gulcu</author>
    <author email="sebastien at qos ddoott ch ">Sebastien Pennec</author>
    <title>Logback Demo</title>
  </properties>
  
	<body>

<h2>Logback Demo</h2>

<p>
	Welcome to the logback demo! This document will take you to a tour
	that will show you some of the major possibilities of logback.
</p>

<h3>Installation</h3>

<p>
	First, please download the logback demo. You will need to install a 
	<a href="http://subversion.tigris.org/">Subversion</a> client
	and issue the following line in a command/terminal window:
</p>
  
<div class="source"><pre>svn co http://svn.qos.ch/repos/logback-demo/trunk logback-demo</pre></div>

<p>
This will checkout a copy of the logback demonstration web-app to a directory called
<em>logback-demo</em>. The logback demo can be packaged as a <em>war</em> file and
deployed to an application server. We strongly recommand the use of 
<a href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven 2</a> to do this
task, since all it will take to compile, package and run a server with the demo is
a single command.
</p>

<p>
	Using Maven, let's package the files and run the demo for the first time. 
  From the <em>logback-demo</em> directory, issue the following command:
</p>

<div class="source"><pre>mvn package jetty:run</pre></div>
    
<p>
	Then, visit <em>http://localhost:8080/logback-demo/</em> to view the main page of the logback demo.
</p>

<p>image main page</p>

<h3>Logback Classic</h3>

<p>
For now, logback uses two components: one <code>ConsoleAppender</code> and one 
<code>RollingFileAppender</code>. The <code>RollingFileAppender</code> sends logging events
to a file called <em>logFile.log</em> and will rollover
the active file every minute. The old file will be renamed and compressed to <em>zip</em>
file. The <code>ConsoleAppender</code> will output the logging requests to the console,
and shorten the logger names to gain some space in the console window, without making the
names unreadable. For example, <code>ch.qos.logback.demo.prime.NumberCruncherImpl
</code> will be displayed as <code>c.q.l.d.prime.NumberCruncherImpl</code>.
</p>

<p>You can study the configuration file that is used by editing the
file called <em>logback.xml</em>, located in the <em>src/main/resources/</em> directory
of the demo. You might want to keep this file in an editor window, since we will
modify its content several times thoughout the demo.
</p>

<p>
Let's now visit the <em>ViewStatii</em> page, via the navigation menu on the left hand
of the navigator window. This page contains the content of the <code>Status</code> objects that were
created until now. <code>Status</code> objects are a part of logback's powerful internal 
reporting framework. They allow you to see what is going on in logback, and check
that a configuration file has been parsed correctly, or that a rollover has occured as 
expected.
</p>

<p>
After you're back to the main window, visiting the <em>View logs</em> page does 
not impress much at the moment. Let us uncomment
the <strong>two</strong> parts of the config file that are below the <em>Cyclic buffer</em> comment.
A <code>CyclicBuffer</code> is a class that keeps track of logging events and holds these
objects for immediate or differed display. The first element that you will need to uncomment
is the <em>appender</em> element. This element describes and configures the <code>CyclicBuffer</code>.
The second element, found at the end of the configuration file, is a <em>appender-ref</em> element.
It is used to link the appender to a given logger.
Now reload the web-app by exiting the previous command with <em>CTRL-C</em> and issuing it
again: <em>mvn package jetty:run</em>.
</p>

<p>
Now, the <em>View logs</em> page looks prettier. By virtue of the <code>CyclicBufferAppender</code>,
this page can fetch the last events and present them through a servlet. We see that each 3 seconds
a line is added to the logs. The formatting of this page is made with
a <code>HTMLLayout</code>. This component creates a nice and readable table containing the logging
events, based on a pattern that describes the information one wants to see in the table.
</p>

<p>
Having the logs that we see on the web page cluttered with scheduled 
<em>Howdydy-diddly-ho</em> messages
is not very comfortable. To get rid of these logs, now that we've verified that they
work, we can add an <code>EvaluatorFilter</code> to the Appender. Uncomment the
part named <em>Cyclic buffer with Evaluator</em>. You may then
comment or delete the first Basic Cyclic buffer <em>appender</em> element.
</p>
<p>
Let's take a look at the filter we've just added:
</p>

<div class="source"><pre>&lt;filter class="ch.qos.logback.core.filter.EvaluatorFilter">
  &lt;evaluator name="loggingTaskEval">
    &lt;expression>
      logger.getName().contains("LoggingTask") &amp;&amp;
      message.contains("Howdydy-diddly-ho") &amp;&amp;
      (timeStamp - event.getStartTime()) >= 20000
    &lt;/expression>
  &lt;/evaluator>
  &lt;OnMatch>DENY&lt;/OnMatch>
&lt;/filter></pre></div>

<p>
The expression element contains a familiar java statement. This expression
checks that the name of the logger contains the String <em>LoggingTask</em>, but
also that the message accompagnying the log contains <em>Howdydy-diddly-ho</em>. 
Moreover, in order to be sure that the <em>Howdydy-diddly-ho</em> task actually
works, we add to the expression a last statement that allows logs to be processed
for the first 20 seconds after the application launch.
The variables used in this statement (<code>logger</code>, <code>message</code> and
<code>event</code>) are made available by logback before the filter 
evaluates the expression.
The <em>OnMatch</em> element allows the user to choose the filter's behaviour once
the expression was evaluated to true. A similar <em>OnMismatch</em> element exists. 
</p>

<p>
After a restart, the <em>Vew logs</em> page shows the
<em>Howdydy-diddly-ho</em> logs for the first 20 seconds only. Trying a prime calculations
on the <em>Prime number</em> page will add several lines to the <em>View logs</em> page.
</p>

<h4>Turbo Filters</h4>

<p>
Logback ships with a special category of filters: <code>TurboFilter</code> objects
are ultra-fast, context-wide filters. They reveals themselves very useful to 
test MDC values, for examples and to add context-wide conditions to allow or deny
logging events. Let's uncomment the part named
<em>TurboFilter: MDC value</em> in the <em>logback.xml</em> file.
</p>
<p>
This part adds a <code>TurboFilter</code> object to the context. It allows to
have a typical output for every client that uses the demo application, but a different
one for one given user. Here, the filter will accept all the requests that are
associated with a MDC value of <em>sebastien</em> bound to the <em>username</em> key.
</p>
<p>
To view the consequences of such a <code>TurboFilter</code>, we are going to
stop all logging activity, except for a specific user. To achieve that, the simplest
way is to set the root logger's level to <code>OFF</code>. Modify the <em>level</em>
element, nested inside the <em>root</em> element of <em>logback.xml</em>. Its <em>value</em>
attribute should be <em>OFF</em> instead of <em>DEBUG</em>. Next, restart the server
as we've done previously.
</p>

<p>
Once on the demo main webpage again, perform a few actions (i.e. calculate
a few prime numbers) and watch the <em>View logs</em> page. The table should be
empty.
</p>

<p>
Now log in the application using the username <em>sebastien</em> and perform a few
prime calculations again. The <em>View logs</em> page now shows the logs that were
generated by the calculation classes. Moreover, each log is associated with the name
of the user who provoked the logging event. Please log off before continuing the
demo, using the <em>logout</em> button on the left.
</p>

<h4>Parametrized logging</h4>

<p>
Parametrized logging is a feature that will be a great asset for any performance-critical
system. Usually, a logging request is issued like this:
</p>

<div class="source"><pre>logger.debug("Hello, my name is" + username + ", I am " + age + " years old.");</pre></div>

<p>
By issuing this line, the cost of constructing the String cannot be saved when the
log request is not processed. For example, using the <code>debug()</code> method
when, as we've just done, the root level is any value higher that <em>DEBUG</em> will 
result in a loss of time because all calls to the <code>debug()</code> method will
eventually be dropped.
</p>

<p>
Logback offers the following method:
</p>

<div class="source"><pre>logger.debug("Hello, my name is {}, I am {} years old", username, age);</pre></div>

<p>
As you can see, the variables are not inserted in the message yet. Both the message
and the values will be saved and used later, if the logging event is processed.
</p>

<p>
Let us now run a test to see what kind of gain can we expect from this different
message formatting approach. First, go to the <em>Prime number</em> page and
run a few calculations. Check the time it takes to compute the results. To
see a clearer difference between the two formatting methods, you might want to
try the two big integers that are listed below the prime number textbox.
</p>

<p>
Now let us edit the <code>NumberCruncherImpl</code> class, to switch the log methods.
You will find this class in the <em>src/main/java/ch/qos/logback/demo/prime/</em>
directory. On line 54 and 55, just uncomment the parametrized logging line and
comment out the other line. Restart the server with <em>mvn package jetty:run</em>
and re-run the calculations you tried beforehand.
</p>

<p>
The durations should be obviously different. Remember that we had turned off all
logging in the previous step of this demo. With the initial formatting method,
we were constructing the logging message (<em>"Trying "+i+" as a factor."</em>) 
a huge amount of times, actually each time a factor was tried for these big numbers.
With the paramatrized logging, the construction of the message was postponed and, since
logging was turned off, not processed. We see here that the cost of the <b>non-</b>logging 
was taken down to a very small figure, dividing the total cost of the calculation
by a non-negligeable factor.
</p>

<h4>Markers</h4>

<p>
SLF4J allows the use of Marker objects. 
For example, one could use <em>TRACE</em> markers, to enrich some 
specific logging statements. On the other hand, one could want that such
marked statements be dropped and not logged anywhere. <code>TurboFilter</code>
objects can do that in an elegant and flexible way. Let us uncomment the
<em>TurboFilter: Marker value</em> section in the <em>logback.xml</em> file as
well as set the root logger's level back to <em>DEBUG</em>,
and reload via the <em>Reload configuration</em> page.
</p>
<p>
The logging statements that contained the <em>Howdydy-diddly-ho</em> do
not appear anymore because they were associated with a <em>TRACE</em> marker. You
can check that by visiting the <em>View Logs</em> page and reloading it every three
seconds for several times.
</p>

<h3>Logback Access</h3>

<p>
Access logging is another important feature offered by logback. Give a 
look at what appears on the console while
browsing the logback-demo website. Each access is logged to the console,
with some information about the event. The configuration file
that we will edit in the next few steps is called <em>logback-access.xml</em>
and is located in the <em>src/etc/</em> directory.
The necessary configuration is listed below:
</p>

<div class="source"><pre>&lt;configuration>
 
  &lt;appender name="STDOUT"
    class="ch.qos.logback.core.ConsoleAppender">
    &lt;layout class="ch.qos.logback.access.PatternLayout">
      &lt;Pattern>%h %l %u %t \"%r\" %s %b&lt;/Pattern>
    &lt;/layout>
  &lt;/appender>
  
  &lt;appender-ref ref="STDOUT" />
  
&lt;/configuration></pre></div>

<p>
To see more clearly the output produced by logback access,
you might want set the root logger's level to <em>OFF</em>, in the first 
logback configuration file, called
<em>logback.xml</em> and located in <em>src/main/resources/</em>. It will clear
the console from the logs made by the demo application and only display those
that are generated by logback access.
</p>

<p>
To see the logs produced by logback access, just visit a few pages and
look at your console. The information contained in each line has been
specified in the configuration file. The <code>ConsoleAppender</code>
named <em>STDOUT</em> contains a <code>PatternLayout</code> component.
This very component that one uses in logback classic to display either
the message, logger name or level of the request is used in logback
access to display the request method, requested page, status code and many others.
</p>

<p>Here is a sample output of this appender.</p>

<div class="source"><pre>127.0.0.1 - - 22/01/2007:14:35:40 +0100 GET /logback-demo/ViewStatii.do HTTP/1.1 200 3660
127.0.0.1 - - 22/01/2007:14:35:41 +0100 GET /logback-demo/index.jsp HTTP/1.1 200 2389
127.0.0.1 - - 22/01/2007:14:35:42 +0100 GET /logback-demo/lastLog/ HTTP/1.1 200 948
127.0.0.1 - - 22/01/2007:14:35:42 +0100 GET /logback-demo/index.jsp HTTP/1.1 200 2389
127.0.0.1 - - 22/01/2007:14:35:43 +0100 GET /logback-demo/prime.jsp HTTP/1.1 200 1296
127.0.0.1 - - 22/01/2007:14:35:44 +0100 GET /logback-demo/index.jsp HTTP/1.1 200 2389
127.0.0.1 - - 22/01/2007:14:35:45 +0100 GET /logback-demo/lottery.jsp HTTP/1.1 200 1209
127.0.0.1 - - 22/01/2007:14:35:46 +0100 GET /logback-demo/index.jsp HTTP/1.1 200 2389
127.0.0.1 - - 22/01/2007:14:35:48 +0100 GET /logback-demo/reload.jsp HTTP/1.1 200 1335
127.0.0.1 - - 22/01/2007:14:35:49 +0100 GET /logback-demo/index.jsp HTTP/1.1 200 2389
127.0.0.1 - - 22/01/2007:14:35:54 +0100 GET /logback-demo/login.jsp HTTP/1.1 200 1214
127.0.0.1 - - 22/01/2007:14:35:55 +0100 GET /logback-demo/Logout.do HTTP/1.1 200 1000</pre></div>

<h4>Filtering</h4>

<p>
In this next part, we are going to add some information to the console.
Let us imagine that we want to log the numbers that are tried on the
<em>Lottery</em> page. We will need a second <code>ConsoleAppender</code>
that will only print a given information (e.g. the guessed number, along
with some hints about the player). The appender will also have to
print that information only when a certain page is accessed.
</p>

<p>
The configuration lines that are necessary are listed below.
</p>

<div class="source"><pre>&lt;appender name="STDOUT_LOTTERY"
  class="ch.qos.logback.core.ConsoleAppender">
  &lt;filter class="ch.qos.logback.core.filter.EvaluatorFilter">
    &lt;evaluator name="lotto_eval">
      &lt;Expression>
        url.matches(event.getRequestURL().toString())
      &lt;/Expression>
      &lt;matcher name="url">
        &lt;regex>Lottery.do&lt;/regex>
        &lt;caseSensitive>false&lt;/caseSensitive>
      &lt;/matcher>
    &lt;/evaluator>
    &lt;OnMatch>ACCEPT&lt;/OnMatch>
    &lt;OnMismatch>DENY&lt;/OnMismatch>
  &lt;/filter>
  &lt;layout class="ch.qos.logback.access.PatternLayout">
    &lt;Pattern>
      LOTTERY: %A [%r] Guess=%reqParameter{guessed_number}
    &lt;/Pattern>
  &lt;/layout>
&lt;/appender></pre></div>

<p>
This appender will use a <code>PatternLayout</code> to format its output.
The <em>%reqParameter</em> conversion word is used to extract the guessed number
from the request, and print it. 
</p>
<p>
It also uses an <code>EvaluatorFilter</code> that will prevent the appender
to display anything when the access' request url does not match the
given expression. You can see that it is easy to specify a RegExp, name
it and use it in the expression that will be evaluated. In that case, we only
entered the name of the <em>lottery.do</em> action.
</p>

<p>
Let us uncomment the two elements with the <em>Lottery to Console</em> comments and
restart the server. Now, try to play the lottery. You will see more lines in the
Console that you've seen until now. At every try, logback will produce a log
as shown below:
</p>

<div class="source"><pre>LOTTERY: 192.168.1.6 [POST /logback-demo/Lottery.do HTTP/1.1] Guess=321</pre></div>

<h4>Sending emails</h4>

<p>
Logback access provides several components that are usually used by the classic
module. For example, a <code>SMTPAppender</code> can be used to send an email when
a specific event occurs. Here, we will contact the lottery administrator each time
a winner is detected. To achieve this, we will add a <code>SMTPAppender</code> to
the existing configuration. Please uncomment the part of <em>logback-access.xml</em>
named <em>Lottery to Email</em>. Do not forget to uncomment the 
<em>appender-ref</em> element, at the end of the configuration file, referencing
the appender called <em>SMTP</em>. In the appender element, notice the use of a
<code>URLEvaluator</code>. This evaluator allows us to only specify one or more URLs
that have to be watched. When one of them are accessed, an email is sent.
</p>

<p>
A reload of the configuration has to be done before we can test this new
component. Once done, try to play the lottery with the number <em>99</em>.
You should see a congratulation message but, most importantly, the
specified recipients should have a new mail in their mailbox. The content
of the email is a nicely formatted HTML table with informations about
the access that have occured before the triggering event.
</p>

<h3>JMX</h3>

<p>
Logback publishes several components via JMX. This allows you to see
the status of certain objects, and change several configuration parameters.
Publishing logback's components via JMX is possible with Jetty and Tomcat.
</p>

<p>
To see logback access' components, visit the following page:
</p>

<div class="source"><pre>http://localhost:8082/</pre></div>

<p>
The domain <em>ch.qos.logback.access.jetty</em> contains an entry
that allows you to see the <em>RequestLogImpl</em> component. This component
is used to plug logback in Jetty's internal achitecture. Clicking on
it reveals the status of several parameters, such as the started status, and
two methods are available to start and stop the <em>RequestLogImpl</em>.
</p>

<p>
To see the influence of the available operations, place the terminal window
and your web browser such that you can see them both. Stop the <em>RequestLogImlp</em>
and reload a few times the main page of the demo. Nothing should be displayed. If you start
the <em>RequestLogImpl</em> again, the requests will be shown in the terminal
window.
</p>

<p>
These is more to discover with logback and JMX. In the <em>logback.xml</em> file, 
placed in the <em>src/main/resources</em> directory, uncomment the <code>JMXConfigurator</code>
element. Once done, restart the server.
</p>

<p>
By refreshing the previously loaded JMX page, you should see a new component,
under the domain <em>ch.qos.logback.classic</em>. It is the <code>JMXConfigurator</code>.
Clicking on it reveals its content. Its possibilities are listed below:
</p>

<ul>
  <p>
    Reload the configuration using the same file that was
    previously used.
  </p>
  <p>
    Reload the configuration using a file whose path is passed as
    a parameter.
  </p>
  <p>
    Reload the configuration using a file whose URL is passed as a
    parameter.
  </p>
  <p>Get the level of a logger</p>
  <p>Change the level setting of a specified logger.</p>
  <p>Change a list of all declared loggers.</p>
  <p>Change the level setting of a specified logger.</p>
</ul>

<p>
  In the last case, you must specify the name of the logger you
  wish to alter, and its new level.
</p>

<p>
Checking the level of a logger is an easy task. Enter the name of the logger in
the appropriate field and click the <em>Invoke</em> button. You should be able
to verify that the logger named <em>root</em> has its level set to <em>OFF</em>.
</p>


<p>
Let us test the level setting possibility of the configurator. 
The <em>Prime Number</em> page requests two types of logs. When the
calculation checks if a number is a factor, a <em>DEBUG</em> log is displayed. When
the calculation has found a factor, a <em>INFO</em> log is displayed. 
</p>

<p>
Let us first set the level of the logger named <em>ch.qos.logback.demo.prime</em>
to <em>DEBUG</em>. Run a prime calculation directly, without restarting the server. The
<em>View logs</em> page should show the <em>DEBUG</em> and <em>INFO</em> logs.
</p>

<p>
Now, if you set the level of the <em>ch.qos.logback.demo.prime</em> logger to 
<em>INFO</em>, and run a prime calculation
again, you should not see the <em>DEBUG</em> level logs anymore.
</p>

<p>
This demo of logback is now over. Do not hesitate to play around with the configuration files.
You might want to check the <a href="http://logback.qos.ch/documentation.html">
logback documentation page</a> for more information about any component
you'd like to test.
</p>

</body>
</document>