<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>

<document>

	<properties>
		<author email="ceki at qos ddoott ch ">Ceki G&#252;lc&#252;</author>
		<title>${pom.name}</title>
	</properties>

	<body>

    <h3>10 reasons to switch to logback</h3>

    <p>
      <a href=" http://tinyurl.com/yjcq33"> <img border="0" src="images/hortisMG.gif"/></a>
    </p>
    
    <p>On the 5th of December, Ceki G&#252;lc&#252; will be presenting
    (in French) top 10 reasons for migrating your projects to
    logback. Issues such as migration strategy, new APIs, SLF4J and
    Joran will be discussed. Emphasis will be given to practical
    aspects and a live demo rather than relatively theoretical
    considerations.
    </p>

    <p>This <a href=" http://tinyurl.com/yjcq33">free-entry event</a>
    is organized in colloboration with <a
    href="http://www.hortis.ch">Hortis SA</a>.</p>

    

		<h2>Logback Project</h2>
		<p>
			Logback is intended as a successor to the popular log4j
			project. It was designed by Ceki G&#252;lcü, the founder of the
			log4j project. It builds upon exerience gained in building
			industrial-strength logging systems going back as far as 1999.
		</p>
		<p>
			Logback's basic architecture is sufficiently generic so as to
			apply under different circumstances. At present time, logback is
			divided into three modules, logback-core, logback-classic and
			logback-access.
		</p>

		<p>
			The logback-core module lays the groundwork for the other two
			modules. The logback-classic module can be assimilated to a
			significantly improved version of log4j. Moreover,
			logback-classic natively implements the <a
			href="http://www.slf4j.org">SLF4J API</a> so that you can
			readily switch back and forth between logback and other logging
			systems such as log4j or JDK14 Logging.

			The Access module integrates with Servlet containers to
			provide HTTP-access log functionality. Note that you can
			easily build your own modules on top of the Core module.
		</p>


	</body>
</document>
